A Guide to the Theodore Dreiser Collection, 1839-1944, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Theodore Dreiser Collection, 1839-1944, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6220-c
This collection consists of 74 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - Diplomatic Society Leaders 1897 Sep 6, AMs. 12 p.
    Essay, with corrections.
  - About the Wharves of New York n.d., AMsS. 26 p.
  - The American Museum of Natural History n.d., AMsS. 27 p.
    Essay.
  - American Women Composers n.d., AMsS. 12 p.
    Essay, with typescript note; includes 3 pages of corrected proofs with clippings.
  - American Women Poets n.d., AMs. 13 p.
  - Cedermere, the Home of William Cullen Bryant n.d., AMsS. 31 p.
    Essay regarding the estate of the poet at Roslyn, Long Island.
  - The Clam Diggers n.d., AMsS. 24 p.
  - Concerning Serious Work and the Indifference of the World n.d., AMsS. 9 p.
    Essay
  - "Concerning Wistfulness and Merriment and a Happy Christmas" n.d., AMsS. 13 p.
  - Cox Electric n.d., AMsS. 12 p.
    Essay regarding H. Barringer Cox, inventor.
  - "Cramp Ship Yards" n.d., AMsS. 30 p.
    Essay regarding a Philadelphia company that built ships for the United States Navy.
  - The Phantom Drunkard n.d., AMs. 21 p.
    Ghost story about Theodore Dreiser's uncle.
  - Sculpture n.d., AMs. 3 p.
    Incomplete essay.
  - "Typebars" n.d., AMs. 14 p.
    Essay regarding printing machines; includes 4 additional pages of notes.
  - Armour Interview n.d., AMsS. 31 p.
    Essay regarding the Armour Institute, Chicago.
  - Interview with John Burroughs n.d., AMs. 3 p.
    Essay; includes 3 pages of magazine clippings with photos.
  - Questions for Interview on Success n.d., AMs. 9 p.
  - Notes n.d., AMs. 2 p.
    Notes for sketch of George Edwin Bissell, American sculptor.
  - Notes n.d., AMs. 4 p.
    Notes for a biographical sketch of Frank Fowler, American painter.
  - Notes n.d., AMs. 2 p.
    Notes on "Daniel Chester French, Sculptor."
  - Notes n.d., AMs. 8 p.
    Notes for a biographical sketch of Frank Wakely Gunsaulus, American clergyman.
  - Thermo-Electricity n.d., AMs. 3 p.
    Notes for an essay regarding an unidentified scientist's life history.
  - Essay regarding William Archer, British drama critic n.d., AMs. 4 p.
  - Essay on nature n.d., AMs. 4 p.
  - Essay n.d., AMs. 7 p.
    Description of a visit to Astoria and Long Island Beach, with corrections.
  - Sketches n.d., AMs. 9 p.
    Sketches of American women artists Alice Barker Stevens, Jessie McDermot, and Curtis Smith; includes magazine clippings on artists Lois Knight and Noble Ives.
  - Sketches n.d., AMs. 17 p.
    Sketches of Helen M. Hemotin, composers [Pietro] Mascagni and [Giacoma] Puccini, cellist Jean Gerandy, and soprano Emma Nevada.
  - Essay on Katherine Bloodgood, American singer n.d., AMs. 4 p.
  - Essay on Germantown, Pennsylvania n.d., AMs. 3 p.
  - Essay on Louise Cox, American painter n.d., Ms, 2 p.
  - Notes and manuscripts n.d., AMs. 19 p.
    Includes biographical and critical essays, an untitled prose poem, and an envelops addressed to Theodore Dreiser in New York City.
  - List of "People who earn their living writing" n.d., AMs. 2 p.
    Includes addresses.
  - List of Women Artists n.d., AMs. 2 p.
    Includes a few addresses.
  - Lists n.d., AMs. 16 p.
    Lists of contributors, harpists, naturalists, readers, and society women of Philadelphia; includes some addresses.
  - List of minor writers n.d., AMs. 8 p.
  - Forward to McDonald's Dreiser Biography, by Theodore Dreiser 1927 Feb 26, Typescript, 2 p.
    Includes corrections.
  - The Cramp Ship Yards of Philadelphia" n.d., Typescript, 18 p. Signed.
  - Essay on American women dramatists n.d., Typescript. 4 p.
  - Essay on United States currency and coins n.d., Typescript. 6 p.
  - Essay on Phillip Armour and Edward Croarkin n.d., Typescript. 4 p.
  - Joseph Hodges Choate 1832- n.d., Typescript. 10 p. Carbon.
    Biographical sketch of an American attorney; includes corrections.
- Letters
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Will M. Clemons 1898 Jun 8, ALS. 1 p.
    Writes two years before publication of his first book; discusses his connection with Ev'ry Month; recalls material submitted to the magazine, which he does not know if they used.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Philadelphia, to Duffy 1903 Jan 6, ALS. 4 p.
    Includes 2 typed copies; writes about friends and family; plans to go to New York one day with a completed novel and ideas that will "shake the universe"; mentions Norman Duncan, Sister Carrie, and The Soul of the Street.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to F. G. Moorhead, Des Moines, Iowa 1909 Apr 5, TLS. 1 p.
    Offers $75 for "Farming DeLuxe" article; intends to use piece in The Designer, but cannot use it in The Delineator; believes Moorhead could write and interesting article on "Farming for Women."
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Professor J. L. Randolph, [Virginia Polytechnic Institute] 1909 Sep 16, TLS. 1 p.
    Invites him to contribute to The Delineator or The New Idea, both of which Dreiser edits; writes that his publications have a circulation of 10,000; asks for suggestions for other contributors.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Edgar Jepson, English novelist 1910 Oct 11, ALS. 4 p.
    Thanks him for kind words regarding Sister Carrie; mentions Gathroyal Gardens, The Delineator, and Tourie; plans to bring [Jennie Gerhardt] out in England.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Nat Kolz 1914 Feb 2, ALS. 2 p.
    Expresses gratitude for dinner.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Miss Wright 1919 Mar 17, ALS. 2 p.
    Autographs Jennie Gerhardt; thanks her for sincere appreciation; mentions "Old Neil House."
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Symon Gould, New York 1919 Sep 15, ALS. 2 p. w/env.
    Intends to include suggested changes to [The Hand of the Potter] in the second edition;mentions his story in the October issue of Smart Set and a review by George Jean Nathan of The Hand of the Potter.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Los Angeles, to David F. Karsner, New York 1920 Dec 12, TLS. 1 p. w/env.
    Thanks him for The Call; agrees with his article "If the Light Should Go Out"; complains about intellectuals; values Lenin and Trotzky greatly over Wells or Wallings.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Blodgett 1922 Dec 12, ALS. 1 p.
    Thanks him for letter written to Chicago Daily News on Dreiser's behalf.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ernest Boyd, New York 1923 Jan 15, ALS. 2 p. w/env.
    Invites him to join [H. L.] Mencken, Sherwood Anderson, A. A. Bull and Tom Smith for a visit.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to George Sterling 1924 Aug 21, TLS 2 p.
    Mentions Dreiser's refusal to look at the work of a young writer, Dr. Abrams, Helen, and Llewellyn Powys.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Ernest Boyd, New York 1925 Apr 16, ALS. 2 p. w/env.
    Invites him to a "Beer drinking adventure" in Brooklyn, at the home of Kenneth Hayes Miller with Ed Smith, [H. L.] Mencken, de Sanchez and others.
  - Theodore Dreiser to Frank [ca. 1926-27], ALS. 1 p.
    Mentions reproductions of paintings and Moods.
  - Theodore Dreiser to William Woodward 1927 Jul 27, ALS. 1 p.
    Accepts invitation for following week; mentions carpentry on Mt. Kisco cabin; asks for directions.
  - Theodore Dreiser to William Woodward 1928 Mar 23, ALS. 1 p.
    Accepts invitation; discusses painful gathering of articles.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to a book shop 1928 Apr 4, ALS. 1 p.
    Requests that a copy of bibliography of his works be forwarded to Otto Kyllmann, president of Constable & Co., his publisher.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to John Cowper Powys 1928 Oct 22, TLS 1 p.
    Plans to return to cabin on December 16; discusses improvements on cabin; mentions Phyllis and Valley Forge.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Margaret Monahan, New York 1929 Jan 9, TLS 1 p.
    Thanks her for list; advises her to get someone to clarify her English before sending manuscript to publisher; plans to discuss her work in person; requests to copy of next revision.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to John Cowper Powys 1930 Nov 26, TLS 1 p.
    Discusses [Charles Hoy] Fort's book; asks for Powys' opinion.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to John Cowper Powys 1930 Dec 12, TLS 1 p.
    Mentions Fortean Society, Mr. Fort, and Powys' letter.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to John Cowper Powys 1931 Dec 21, TLS 1 p.
    Believes he is finally cured of stomach ulcers.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to John Cowper Powys 1932 Sep 8, ALS. 2 p.
    Describes purpose of The American Spectator, a monthly edited by Dreiser and others; invites him to submit a piece, which will be printed as written for $.01 a word.
  - Theodore Dreiser, Mt. Kisco, New York, to John Cowper Powys 1932 Sep 29, TLS 1 p.
    Likes his article very much; writes that there is no room for it in the current issue.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to John Cowper Powys, Hillsdale, New York 1932 Nov 21, TLS 1 p.
    Writes that Boyd, Nathan, Cabell, and O'Neill would not accept his article; mentions The Spectator.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Frank C. Dodd, New York 1934 Apr 30, TLS 1 p.
    Expresses thanks.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Clark 1938 Oct 3, ALS. 2 p.
    Mentions Bye, John Wheeler, the Syndicate, book of 12 stories, and writing an introduction.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Clark 1938 Oct 20, ALS. 2 p.
    Asserts that 6 of the stories are okay and will go to Gingrich with Dreiser's endorsement; requests he send all of the stories.
  - Theodore Dreiser, New York, to Theodore Fred Kuper, New York 1944 Apr 14, TLS 1 p. w/env.
    Thanks him for forwarding Claude Bowers letter, which Dreiser has just answered.
- Miscellaneous
  - Various clippings 1898 Jan, Clippings
    Includes: article by Theodore Dreiser on Joseph Choate, 1 p., from Success, January, 1898; "A Talk with America's Leading Author, or What Success Means," 2 p. with illustration; articles on "The Great Harbor Improvement," New York Herald, 1881, July 25 and other dates, with discussion of Sandy Hook bar and deepening of ship channels; "The Evolution of the Typewriter," 8 page reprint from Bedford's, April, 1892; "The Sailor's Harbor" by Mrs. R. F. Woodward, 9 pages with photos.
  - Reviews 1839 Mar 8, Clippings
    Cover review from New York Times Book Review Magazine by Maxwell Geisman; review of The Letters of Theodore Dreiser, edited by Robert H. Elias with photos, from the University of Pennsylvania Library.
  - Portraits of Theodore Dreiser, signed n. d., Photographs
    Folder includes: profile at middle age, 8"x10"; magazine photo from New York Library Picture Collection, Dreiser, head and shoulders, 4"x5"; painting, "An American Tragedy-Theodore Dreiser," caricature by William Cotton for Vanity Fair, 1931 volume 37, no. 2, head and shoulders, 8"x10".